Guide to the John R. Gregg Papers, 1947-2009 UA.29.02.0251
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John R. Gregg papers
1947-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gregg, John, Dr.
Duke University. Department of Zoology -- Faculty
UA.29.02.0251
4 Linear Feet
John R. Gregg, former professor of zoology, was born December 16, 1916. He received his undergraduate degree from the University of Alabama, and then completed a Ph.D. in biology at Princeton in 1946. For a decade, he served on the faculty at Columbia University before coming to Duke in 1957. He stayed at Duke until his retirement in 1986. Gregg was also a skilled longbow archer and his papers contain some information about archery. In 2009, he died at the age of 92. The John Gregg Papers contain mostly information about Dr. Gregg's research and work including materials related to the courses he taught. His interest in archery is also reflected. The collection also contains significant correspondence between Gregg and J.H. Woodger, an influential 20th century British theoretical biologist and philosopher of biology.
Access to Collection
Collection is open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John R. Gregg (1916-2009) was a Biological Science Professor Emeritus at Duke University. After earning an undergraduate degree from the University of Alabama and his PhD from Princeton University, Gregg served as a professor in the Duke University Zoology department from 1957 to his retirement in 1986. During his time at Duke, Gregg served as the acting chair of the Zoology department chair from 1958-1959 and as director of graduate studies from1968-1971. Gregg authored 33 publications during his academic career including two books, The Language of Taxonomy (1954) and Form and Strategy (1963). His work on taxonomic systems in The Language of Taxonomy led to the development of the "Gregg Paradox".
During the summer of 1967, he led the Undergraduate Institute for Theoretical Biology sponsored by NASA. During his career, Gregg collaborated closely with British biologist Joseph Henry Woodger, the developer of the influential Axiomatic Method.In addition to his scientific work, Gregg was extremely passionate about archery and donated his collection of antique bows and other artifacts to the Smithsonian Museum.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the academic and personal papers of John R. Gregg, Professor Emeritus of Zoology at Duke University. The collection includes correspondence between Gregg and leading biologists such as Joseph Henry Woodger and Arstrid Lindenmayer and notes and drafts of Gregg's many publications, research notes on a variety of subjects in Biology and Zoology, and materials related to lectures given by Gregg. The collection also reflects Gregg's experiences as a professor of Zoology at Duke University with lecture notes and class materials relating to classes he taught. Materials also include personal papers relating to Gregg's passionate interest in archery, including blueprints and designs of archery equipment created by Gregg.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transfer; October 22, 2012
Archery; Zoology -- Study and teaching (Higher); Biology--Classification; Numerical taxonomy; Duke University. Department of Biology.
- Research, 1947-2009; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Research series contains notes, publications and other materials that Gregg collected and employed during his research in Zoology. The Publications subseries deals with materials related to publications authored by Gregg during his career, including his 1954 book, The Language of Taxonomy. Also included are book reviews of other publications published by Gregg. Materials in this subseries are organized alphabetically by title. Materials include drafts of the publications containing edits and annotations, source lists and notes that Gregg took while preparing the publications. Also included are Gregg's notes relating to an unfinished manuscript from 1963 on developmental energetics. The Research Notes subseries contains materials related to different research subjects, organized alphabetically by title as well as several bound notebook containing notes by Gregg. The Lectures subseries contains materials related to lecture talks given by Gregg during his career, including his 1958 lecture in Europe.
  - Publications, 1
    - Abstract Machines (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Analytical Natural Deduction, 1967- (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Axiomatic Quasi-Natural Deduction, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Buck and Hull: A Critical Rejoiner, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A Calculus of Individuals, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - A Calculus of Q-Individuals, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cytogenetics, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Developmental Energetics (Unfinished Manuscript), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Developmental Systems, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Explication: The Concept of Cell (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Finite Linnean Systems, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Language of Taxonomy, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - A New Version of Quantification Theory, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - On Natural Deduction, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - [Book Reviews] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - On Deciding Whether Protisans are Cells (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - A Technique for Natural Deduction, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Two Modes of Deductive Interference, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Research Notes, 2
    - Haxbu: a begins u, x is environment of u and b ends u, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - LE(2); u (X,13) combined (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Reduction To Valid Sequences, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Singulatory Genetical Systems (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Protazoa and Cells (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - The System (E(F G I)1) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - The System (F G I)1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - The System (F G I)2 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Taxonomic Systems with a Finite Number of Ranks, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - The Theory of LE (2) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Theory of µ(?,?) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Theorums P, T (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - XE, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - D, F, G, E, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Misc Notes (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - [Blue Binder Notes] (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - General Reading, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - [Black Binder Notes] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - [Notebook 1] (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - [Notebook 2] (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - [Notebook 3] (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - [Notebook 4] (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - [Notebook 5] (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lectures, 3
    - Visit to Tankhurst, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Studies in the Topic of Evolutionary Genetics: Talk given at Gainesville (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Talk, Raleigh, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Class Lecture Notes, 1947-2009; 2
  The Class Lecture Notes series contains materials Gregg used for teaching in the Zoology department at Duke University. Materials include lesson notes, tests and source lists related to individual classes taught by Gregg, as well as notes and sources Gregg compiled to teach general topics in Zoology such as regeneration and nuclear differentiation.
  - Nuclear Differentiation, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Regeneration, 1955-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Energies of Development, 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Energies of Development, 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Zoology I (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Zoology 92: Laboratory Record + Instructions (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Zoology 196s.58, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Zoology 205, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Zoology 229:Axiation (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lectures to Zoology 271: Cell Physiology, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Zoology 229: Gametogenisis, Fertilization (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Zoology 205 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Zoology 295, 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Zoology 295 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lectures Biology 14.6, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Archery, 1947-2009; 3
  The Archery series includes materials related to Gregg's hobby of archery and contains correspondence between Gregg and manufacturers of archery equipment, designs of archery equipment created by Gregg and his 1982 manuscript, Elements of Longbow Design. This series also contains notes on Gregg's efforts to donate the archery collection of his friend Russell G. Wilcox to the Smithsonian Institution.
  - Dwight G. Gorrell (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Al Herrin (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Robert S. John (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Val Rawnsley (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Earl L. Ullrich (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Russell G. Wilcox (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Wilcox Estate (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - O. M. Wilsey (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Archery Photographs (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Actual Designs, 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Actual Designs, 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Bow Weight, Arrow Deflection and Arrow Length (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Braced Bow Curvatures (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Cherokee D (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - D-Bow Curvature Variation (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Elements of Longbow Design, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Notes and Designs (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Power Law Limb Curvature (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - [Misc Archery Notes] (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Flat Iron (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, 1947-2009; 4
  The Correspondence series contains letters and postcards written to and from Gregg. The subseries J.H. Woodger contains correspondence related to the professional collaboration and personal friendship between Gregg and the British biological philosopher Joseph Henry Woodger beginning in 1954 and ending with Woodger's death in 1974. Many of the materials reflect the development of the axiomatic theory including Woodger's comments on Gregg's work and ideals and copies of notes and lectures sent to Gregg by Woodger. The correspondence also includes materials related to a trip by Woodger to the United States and his visit to Gregg in Durham. Folders within this subseries are organized chronologically. The general correspondence subseries contains other letters received by Gregg including his correspondence with Hungarian biologist Aristid Lindenmayer, the developer of the Lindenmayer system and other correspondence received by Gregg during his career.
  - J.H. Woodger
    - Woodger Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Woodger Correspondence, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Woodger Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Woodger Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Woodger Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Woodger Correspondence, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence
    - Lindenmayer Correspondence, 1957-1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Photo from Joanne Werts (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Misc. Correspondence, 1957-1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)